

Ashish Gupta

Social Entrepreneurship and Technology Expert

Passionate Entrepreneur with over 20+ years of strong Leadership experience in Sustainability (Agriculture), Research, Resilience, Future Systems Thinking and Technology. Aiming to co-create systems to help scale up sustainability benefits (social, ecological and economic) using creative out-of-box thinking and Technology.

embed.ashishg@gmail.com

+91.9810348193

9

Delhi, India

in linkedin.com/in/guptaji

SKILLS

Branding and Brand Management

End of Life Cycle Thinking

Entrepreneurial Development

Market Linkage Model Design

Market Placement and Marketing

Product Development

Project-Team Management

Resilience and Crisis Management

Strategic Planning

First Principles Thinking

Sustainability Impact Analysis

True Cost Accounting

Sustainable Development Goals Systems

Systems Architecture

Systems Thinking Strategic Leadership

WORK EXPERIENCE

Entrepreneurial Roles

Organic Way of Life (Jaivik Haat), Jaivik Haat Private Limited (JHPL)

10/2009 – Present Delhi, India

Achievements/Tasks

- 100% Single Handed Successful Business Establishment from ground-up for 10+ years. Successful Compliance and Crisis Management during events like COVID-19 lockdown for business continuity.
- Assisted over 3000 farmers in over 10 years to establish localized and interconnected markets. Advised Government of India (Ministry
 of Agriculture) and Food Safety Regulator FSSAI (Ministry of Health) on Organic Farming and Food Standards and Systems for India.
- Achieved sales turnover of INR 40 lacs+ (upto INR 70 lacs+) from 3rd Year Onward with Negligible debt exposure. Break-even achieved 3rd Year Onward. Increased Turnover over 30% Y-o-Y by suitable sourcing, networking and marketing interventions.
- Created Systems for transparency and fair prices for farmers assisted other farmers and clusters in entrepreneurship through online business models (Kalasan Nursery Farm) and Millet value processing for end markets.

 ✓
- Successfully developed Products (Organic Foods) with Branding, Market Placement strategies for farmer clusters in Himachal Pradesh, Jharkhand, Odisha and West Bengal. Localized marketing in regions and in Delhi for retail strategies and income enhancement of farmers.
- Successfully transferred running Business via Corporate Formation, Compliances, Valuation, Taxation and Finance.

Consulting - Sustainable Food Systems Expert

Various Organisations (IFOAM-OI,FAO, WHH, APO)

Food and Agriculture Organisation of United Nations (FAO), Welthungerhilfe (WHH), Asia Productivity Organisation (APO)

Achievements/Tasks

05/2014 - 07/2019

Delhi, India

- Served as First Vice President IFOAM-Asia. Member of PGS and Innovations Committee IFOAM-OI. Presented at IFAD Governing Council 5th Farmers Forum on Sustainable Agriculture.
- Advised FAO on Sustainable Food Systems Capacity Development, Sustainable Development Goals (SDG 2.4.1) Frameworks,
 Participatory Guarantee Systems (PGS), Big-Data Analytics for Smallholder farming clusters in India. Prepared Training Modules for Ministry of Rural Development on Agroecology systems in India.
- Assisted APO with creation of Training Programs on Social Entrepreneurship for Rural Development for Government Employees and NGOS for 18 countries in Asia.
- Created Scalable Food Systems Platform for WHH for connecting 5 NGOS and over stakeholders 3000 farmers to localized markets.
 Advised the G7 (German Presidency 2015) Countries Network on Sustainable Agriculture Impact for Global South.
- Published 6 research papers, journals on Sustainable Agriculture Nationally and Internationally on Pricing, Standards, Non-Timber Forest Produce, Smallholders and Food Systems.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Social Leadership Roles

Various (Gram Disha Trust - GDT, Delhi Organic Farmers Market Trust - DOFM, OFAI, PGSOC)

02/2010 – Present India

Various National, International Non-Profits working on Sustainable Agriculture and Market for Farmers

Achievements/Tasks

- Successfully Co-Founded multiple Trusts (GDT and DOFM) as per Legal Compliances including designing suitable objectives and statues. Principle of establishment for these Non-Profits is to serve Sustainable Agriculture Systems and Smallholder farmer livelihood impact.
- Designed and Implemented Programs for Sustainable Agriculture, Craft and Mountain Development in GDT. Created and Mentored
 Interns (Short term and long term) from Agriculture, Business and Skill development institutional programs.
- Co-Created formal market systems, protocols based on transparency and fairness for farmers from Delhi's Oldest Organic Farmers
 Market (DOFM). Created and managed protocols for enabling transparency and trust between producer-consumer-intermediary.
- Served as Board member and contributed to organisation development, board meetings and Advocacy for Sustainable Agriculture in Indias largest network - Organic Farming Association of India (OFAI).
- Served as Secretary Board for PGS Organic Council for board management, protocol and framework development for PGS
 Certification, Marketing and Event Promotion for farmers for 12 NGOs across India.

Technology Leadership Brief (Computer Engineering and Software Development) Various Companies (GISIL Designs, Conexant Systems, NIKSUN, Pixtel Communications, iPolicy Networks)

07/2000 – 08/2008 India

Achievements/Tasks

- Developed Solutions for Secure PoS terminals, Biometric Compliance (ISO 19794), PCI DSS Compliance for PED EMV Level 2 Kernel, Cryptography applications, Processor Virtualization for ARM7 and USIP.
- Performed various roles for Data and Control Path development for IPSEC VPN, Intrution Detection, QOS, Firewall and Packet Classification for ADSL Modem and DSLAM, OS Kernel Embedding, Board Bringup.
- Developed interfaces for MMI, Call Management state machine and Protocol Stack Integration for ARM based GSM/GPRS Chipset.
- Managed and mentored multiple technical engineers in various IT Projects from large and small enterprises for successful project delivery and deployment. Kept focus on cost reduction and profit optimization by appropriate technological solutions.

HONOR AWARDS

Global Organic Ambassador (09/2014 - Present)

International Federation of Organic Agriculture Movements (IFOAM-OI)

Awarded in Organic World Congress, Istanbul Turkey

EDUCATION (HIGHEST)

Master of Science - Software SystemsBirla Institute of Technology and Sciences

06/2002 – 07/2004 9.10/10.0

CERTIFICATES

Free Prior Informed Consent (FPIC) (12/2018 – Present) Food and Agriculture Organisations (FAO) of the United Nations

Resilience in Food Security Analysis (11/2018 – Present) Food and Agriculture Organisations (FAO) of the United Nations

ACHIEVEMENTS

Presented on Sustainable Agriculture at G7 (German Presidency) (05/2014 − 07/2015)

✓

Advocacy presentation to Sherpas for G7 Presidency on 'Sustainable Agriculture - Nurtition and the G7' in April 2015. Co-Created the "Berlin Memorandum" for formal submission to the G7.

Post Graduate Thesis (06/2003 – 07/2004)

InterWeave - A Novel Network Processor Architecture for Active Networks. Details requirements of Active networks and challenges in implementing them. Proposes architecture to support such networks.

Presented at 5th IFAD Farmer Forum 2014 (02/2014 – 02/2014) ♂

Presented to Governing Council in 5th IFAD farmers forum for advocating Sustainable Agriculture in India and the Global South.

Research Paper Presentation - First Prize (1997)

Presented paper titled "Computer Simulation and Modeling" at National Level Presentation held at REC Kurukshetra and BITS Pilani. The paper elucidates various mathematical and empirical approaches to Computer Simulations and Modeling.

ORGANIZATIONS

Gram Disha Trust (09/2019 − Present)
Founding Trustee

Delhi Organic Farmers Market Trust (01/2019 − Present) ☑

Founding Trustee

PUBLICATIONS

Book

Enabling Sustainable Food Systems - Innovators Handbook

Multiple

List of Authors

In press

FAO-INRA

Research paper

Participatory Guarantee System (PGS) for NTFPs measurement and management - complexities and opportunities

Gupta A.

Naidu P.

2015

FAO - XI World Forestry Congress

http://www.fao.org/about/meetings/world-forestry-congress/programme/technical-papers-and-posters/en/

Paper Presentation

Managing Prices for Sustainable Agricultural Food Systems: Challenges and Opportunities

Gupta A.

Loconto A, Udupa N

2017

IFOAM-OI Organic World Congress

https://goo.gl/YUUtmF

Chapter

Participatory Guarantee Systems (PGS) – A Case of Small holders in the Indian Markets

Gupta A.

List of Authors

2016

FAO

http://www.fao.org/sustainable-food-value-chains/library/details/en/c/430196/

SUPPORTED CAUSES

Ahinsa and Gandhism

Animal Welfare

Crisis Relief

Food Safety and Nutrition

Sustainable Agriculture and Forestry

INTERESTS

Backpacking and Travelling

Composting

Horticulture - Fruit Trees and Vegetables

Mountaineering

Music - Guitar/Flute Play